# Yongjoo Park

Computer Science and Engineering University of Michigan 2260 Hayward St. 4957 Beyster Ann Arbor, MI 48109-2121 Website: https://yongjoopark.com Email: pyongjoo@umich.edu Voice: +1 (734) 707-9206

# RESEARCH INTEREST

Database Systems, Big Data, Data Analytics, Machine Learning

My research interest is **systems for fast data analytics and machine learning** (ML), with a special focus on exploiting *quality-performance tradeoffs* for substantially faster performance. I combine rigorous statistical theories and systems understanding to build *fast*, *quality-guaranteed* data analytics and ML systems.

EDUCATION & TRAINING

Research Fellow September 2017–Present

University of Michigan, Ann Arbor

• Principal Investigator: Barzan Mozafari

Ph.D., Computer Science and Engineering

August 2017

University of Michigan, Ann Arbor

- · Thesis Title: Fast Analytics by Learning
- Advisors: Michael Cafarella and Barzan Mozafari

M.S., Computer Science June 2013

University of Michigan, Ann Arbor

B.S., Electrical Engineering February 2009

Seoul National University (SNU), South Korea

RESEARCH

Despite its massive performance benefits, exploiting the quality-performance tradeoffs in analytic and ML workloads is challenging due to their *non-linearity* and *data-/workloads-dependencies*. My research investigates and exploits these intricate tradeoff relationships for building fast data analytics and ML systems, which can be considered in three (not mutually exclusive) categories, i.e., data analytics, machine learning, and self-learning analytics.

#### **Data Analytics**

- Aggregation: VerdictDB is the first approximate query processing system that *can run on top of any SQL engines*. VerdictDB addresses the challenge of *platform-independent accuracy-guarantees* by proposing a highly-efficient, SQL-friendly error-estimation technique.
- Visualization: Visualization-Aware Sampling (VAS) is an optimal sampling technique for scatter plot *visualization*. VAS answers the following question: what is the optimal subset of data if we want to maximize the overall quality of visualization?
- Searching: Neighbor-Sensitive Searching (NSH) is an algorithm for approximate *k-nearest* neighbor search. NSH relies on an intuitive idea: for *k*NN, the distances between close items must be captured more accurately than the distances between other items.

### **Machine Learning**

BlinkML is a fast ML system with probabilistic quality guarantees. BlinkML automatically and
efficiently determines the minimum sample size such that the model trained on that sample
produces the identical predictions as the full model (trained on the entire data) with high probability.

### **Self-Learning Analytics**

- Aggregation: Database learning (DBL) is an approximate query processing system that produces increasingly more accurate answers as it processes more queries. DBL relies on a non-parametric probabilistic model of the underlying data, constructed using the answers to past queries.
- Selectivity Estimation: QuickSel is a selectivity estimation algorithm that becomes more accurate as it processes more queries.

### IMPACT ACADEMIC IMPACT

I have first-authored five research papers in premier database conferences (e.g., SIGMOD, VLDB). Part of this work was awarded **2018 ACM SIGMOD Jim Gray Dissertation Award runner-up.** Most of my systems and algorithms are open-sourced.

#### INDUSTRY IMPACT

VerdictDB has been adopted by Walmart for its data analytics and by Digital2Go for its cloud platforms.

- Walmart analyzes a massive amount of its sales data for email marketing; VerdictDB speeds up their ad-hoc analytic queries.
- Digital2Go uses the user check-in data for its mobile advertising, and the ability to quickly estimate the number of target mobile devices is desired; VerdictDB offers a cost-efficient solution.

VerdictDB is also tested by several other companies (Alibaba, Tableau) and is studied by students and researchers at other institutions.

June 2018

2004

• 2018 ACM SIGMOD Jim Gray Dissertation Award runner-up

#### **AWARDS**

•	<b>,</b>
ACM SIGMOD Student Travel Award, USD 900	May 2017
Rackham Travel Grant, USD 800	Jan 2017
<ul> <li>Graduate Study Fellowship (for Ph.D.), USD 100,000</li> <li>Kwanjeong Education Foundation</li> <li>The biggest scholarship foundation in Korea</li> </ul>	2013
<ul> <li>Graduate Study Fellowship (for Masters), USD 55,000</li> <li>Jeongsong Cultural Foundation</li> </ul>	2011

### **PUBLICATION**

### **Referred Conference Papers**

One of only eight recipients in 2011

• Korean National Science Scholarship, USD 20,000

- Yongjoo Park, Jingyi Qing, Xiaoyang Shen, Barzan Mozafari BlinkML: Efficient Maximum Likelihood Estimation with Probabilistic Guarantees SIGMOD'19 (research): ACM SIGMOD/PODS International Conference on Management of Data, Amsterdam, The Netherlands, 2019.
- Yongjoo Park, Barzan Mozafari, Joseph Sorenson, Junhao Wang VerdictDB: Universalizing Approximate Query Processing SIGMOD'18 (research): ACM SIGMOD/PODS International Conference on Management of Data, Houston, TX, USA, 2018.

3. Wen He, Yongjoo Park, Idris Hanafi, Jacob Yatvitskiy, Barzan Mozafari

Demonstration of VerdictDB, the Platform-Independent AQP System

**SIGMOD'18** (demo): ACM SIGMOD/PODS International Conference on Management of Data, Houston, TX, USA, 2018.

4. Yongjoo Park, Amhad Shahab Tajik, Michael Cafarella, Barzan Mozafari

Database Learning: Toward a Database System that Becomes Smarter Over Time

**SIGMOD'17** (research): ACM SIGMOD/PODS International Conference on Management of Data, Chicago, IL, USA, 2017.

SIGMOD Travel Award

5. Yongjoo Park

### **Active Database Learning**

**CIDR'17** (abstract): The biennial Conference on Innovative Data Systems Research, Chaminade, CA, USA, 2017.

6. Yongjoo Park, Michael Cafarella, Barzan Mozafari

**Visualization-Aware Sampling for Very Large Databases** 

ICDE 2016 (research): IEEE 32nd International Conference on Data Engineering, Helsinki, Finland, 2016.

7. Yongjoo Park, Michael Cafarella, Barzan Mozafari

**Neighbor-Sensitive Hashing** 

**VLDB'16** (research): 42nd International Conference on Very Large Data Bases, New Delhi, India, 2016.

8. Michael Anderson, Dolan Antenucci, Victor Bittorf, Matthew Burgess, Michael Cafarella, Arun Kumar, Feng Niu, **Yongjoo Park**, Christopher Ré, Ce Zhang

**Brainwash: A Data System for Feature Engineering** 

**CIDR 2013** (vision): The biennial Conference on Innovative Data Systems Research, Asilomar, CA, USA, 2013.

### In Submission

9. Yongjoo Park, Shucheng Zhang, Barzan Mozafari

QuickSel: Quick Selectivity Learning with Mixture Models

In Submission (research)

### **Workshop Presentations (without Proceedings)**

10. Yongjoo Park, Amhad Shahab Tajik, Michael Cafarella, Barzan Mozafari

# **Building Databases that Become Smarter over Time**

MBDOC'16: Midwest Big Data Opportunities and Challenges Workshop, Chicago, IL, USA, 2016

11. Yongjoo Park, Amhad Shahab Tajik, Michael Cafarella, Barzan Mozafari

Database Learning: Toward a Database System that Becomes Smarter Over Time NEDB'16: North East Database Day 2016 (oral), Boston, MA, USA, 2016.

12. Yongjoo Park, Michael Cafarella, Barzan Mozafari

### **Neighbor-Sensitive Hashing**

VSM'16: 3rd Workshop on Web-scale Vision and Social Media at ICCV (Extended Abstract), Santiago, Chile, 2015.

#### **Thesis**

13. Yongjoo Park

### **Fast Data Analytics by Learning**

Ph.D. Dissertation

Awarded 2018 ACM SIGMOD Jim Gray Dissertation Award runner-up

# Non-Referred Technical Reports (full versions to published papers)

- 14. Yongjoo Park, Barzan Mozafari, Joseph Sorenson, Junhao Wang VerdictDB: Universalizing Approximate Query Processing
- 15. Yongjoo Park, Amhad Shahab Tajik, Michael Cafarella, Barzan Mozafari

  Database Learning: Toward a Database System that Becomes Smarter Over Time
- Yongjoo Park, Michael Cafarella, Barzan Mozafari Neighbor-Sensitive Hashing
- 17. Yongjoo Park, Michael Cafarella, Barzan Mozafari
  Visualization-Aware Sampling for Very Large Databases

#### TALKS BlinkML

1. AVL (www.avl.com), Ann Arbor, April 2018

#### VerdictDB

- 2. Oracle BI Group, Redwood City, December 2017
- 3. ACAIA workshop, San Jose, November 2017
- 4. Oracle Database Group, Redwood City, November 2017
- 5. Cloudera Impala Team, Palo Alto, November 2017
- 6. Big Data Innovation Summit, Boston, Septempber 2017
- 7. New Tech Meetup, Ann Arbor, July 2017
- 8. SIGMOD, Chicago, May 2017
- 9. University of Michigan Software Group, Ann Arbor, May 2017

### **Database Learning**

- 10. Brown Database Group, Providence, March 2017
- 11. Stanford InfoLab, Palo Alto, February 2017
- 12. CIDR, Chaminade, California, January 2017
- 13. MBDOC, Chicago, September 2016
- 14. NEDB, Boston, January 2016

# **Visualization-Aware Sampling**

- 15. ICDE, Helsinki, Finland, May 2016
- 16. AVL (www.avl.com), Ann Arbor, April 2016

# **Neighbor-Sensitive Hashing**

- 17. VLDB, New Delhi, India, September 2016
- 18. VSM@ICCV, Santiago, Chile, December 2015

#### **TEACHING**

# Guest Lecturer, Advanced Database Management Systems (EECS 584)

University of Michigan, Fall 2018

· Led the sections for streaming database systems

#### Guest Lecturer, Database Management Systems (EECS 484)

University of Michigan, Winter 2018

· On approximate database systems

### Graduate Student Instructor, Web Databases and Information Systems (EECS 485)

University of Michigan, Winter 2012

- Designed programming assignments (interactive web using JavaScript, and PageRank computation of Wikipedia pages using Hadoop)
- · Led weekly discussion sessions

#### **MENTORING**

#### Wen He (B.S.)

Summer 2017-Winter 2018

Wen He and I implemented **VerdictDB**'s driver for Apache Spark SQL and tested the driver on top of various platforms, such as Cloudera cluster, MapR cluster, and Google's Dataproc. Wen authored **our demo paper** published in SIGMOD 2018. Wen He joined the master's program at Carnegie Mellon University.

### **Shucheng Zhong (B.S.)**

2018

Shucheng Zhong and I implemented **VerdictDB**'s query parsing and planning logic. He also contributed, **QuickSel**, the selectivity estimation algorithm that becomes more accurate over time. He is the co-author on the corresponding research paper. He applies to graduate programs this year.

### Jingyi Qing (B.S.)

Fall 2017-Winter 2018

I and Jingyi Qing developed **BlinkML**, the system that can quickly train ML models with probabilistic accuracy guarantees. He is the co-author on the corresponding research paper. Jingyi Qing joined Amazon.com, Seattle.

# Xiaoyang Shen (B.S.)

Fall 2017-Winter 2018

I worked with Xiaoyang Shen on developing and testing **BlinkML**, which appears in SIGMOD 2019. Xiaoyang Shen applies to graduate programs this year.

#### Junhao Wang (B.S.)

Summer 2017-Fall 2018

I worked with Junhao Wang to implement **VerdictDB**'s driver for Amazon Redshift. He is a coauthor of the corresponding research paper published in SIGMOD 2018. Junhao Wang joined the master's program at McGill University.

#### **EMPLOYMENT**

Graduate Student Research Assistant University of Michigan, Ann Arbor

Fall 2012-Winter 2017

# Software Engineer Intern

Summer 2014

Amazon.com, Seattle

 Developed a data center capacity prediction system for all Amazon data centers

### Graduate Student Instructor

Winter 2012

University of Michigan, Ann Arbor

• EECS 485 Web Databases and Information Systems (see TEACHING for details)

### Software Engineer

Dec 2008-May 2011

Webcash, Seoul

- · Developed an online banking system for J.P. Morgan, Hong Kong
- · Developed financial iPhone applications

Research Assistant

June 2007-Jan 2008

Seoul National University, Seoul

• Developed a power-efficient vehicle entertainment system that runs on embedded-processors (ARM)

#### **SERVICE**

Reviewer, TKDE 2018

Program Committee, aiDM workshop at SIGMOD 2018 (http://www.aidm-conf.org/)

Reviewer, SIGMOD 2018

Publicity Chair, ACAIA workshop 2017 (http://dbgroup.eecs.umich.edu/acaia/)

Reviewer, VLDBJ 2017

External reviewer

- SIGMOD 2019
- VLDB 2018
- CIDR 2017
- VLDBJ, VLDB, SIGMOD 2016
- VLDB, ICDE, CIDR 2015

# Organizer of

- University of Michigan Database Group meetings 2016, 2014
- MIDAS (Michigan Data Science) seminars 2014

# REFERENCES

# Michael J. Cafarella

Associate Professor

The University of Michigan, Ann Arbor http://web.eecs.umich.edu/~michjc/

michjc@umich.edu

# Barzan Mozafari

Assistant Professor The University of Michigan, Ann Arbor http://web.eecs.umich.edu/~mozafari/ mozafari@umich.edu

# Jeffrey F. Naughton

Emeritus Professor The University of Wisconsin, Madison The head of Google Madison http://pages.cs.wisc.edu/~naughton/ naughton@google.com

# Srikanth Kandula

Principal Researcher Microsoft Research https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/research/people/srikanth/ srikanth@microsoft.com